A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Business Records, 1831-1904, undated
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Albemarle County (Va.) Business Records, 1831-1904, undated
Library of Virginia
8 volumes; 7 microfilm reels.
Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Albemarle County in an undated accession.
Alternative Form Available
Please see Albemarle County Microfilm index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
John S. Crawford Plantation Account Book, 1859-1869 is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 234
William J. Ficklin Account Book, 1902-1904 is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 230
William T. McAllister Daybook, 1876-1877 is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 230
Price, Phares and Randolph Real Estate Listings, undated is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 230
John B. Spiece Plantation Ledger, 1831-1890 (bulk 1857-1890) is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 232
Unidentified Newspaper Account Book, 1831-1836 is available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 234
Woods and Company Order Book and Account Book No. 4, 1897-1898 are available as microfilm Albemarle County (Va.) Reel 231
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle, and governor of Virginia from 1737 to 1754. It was created by a statute of 1744 and formed from Goochland County; part of Louisa County was added in 1761 and islands in the Fluvanna (now the James) River in 1770. The court met for the first time on 8 February 1745. The county seat is the city of Charlottesville. Area: 722.6 square miles. Population: 94,186 (2000), 90,400 (2005 estimate)
Lost Records Locality: Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Created in 1744. All order books except the first and many loose papers between 1748 and 1781 were destroyed by British general Banastre Tarleton's raid on Charlottesville in 1781 during the Revolutionary War.
Scope and Content
Albemarle County (Va.) Business Records, 1831-1904, are comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Albemarle County (Va.) Represented records consist of bound volumes such as ledgers, account books, a daybook, real estate listings and an order book.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: John S. Crawford Plantation Account Book, 1859-1869
Series II: William J. Ficklin Account book, 1902-1904
Series III: C. R. Mann Book C, 1879-1880
Series IV: William T. McAllister Daybook, 1876-1877
Series V: Price, Phares, and Randolph real estate listings, undated
Series VI: John B. Spiece Plantation Ledger, 1831-1890 (bulk 1857-1890)
Series VII: Unidentified Newspaper Account Book, 1831-1836
Series VIII: Woods and Company Records, 1897-1898
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also Albemarle County (Va.) Chancery Cause, Wingo, Ellett and Crump, etc. vs. Mann and Wood, 1890-022.
Related Material
Additional Albemarle County(Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Related Material
Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Albemarle County records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
Contents List
- John S. Crawford Plantation Account Book, 1859-1869, 1 volume
  Historical Information: John S. Crawford was a prominent landowner in Bath County, Virginia.
  Scope and Content: John S. Crawford Plantation Account Book, 1859-1869, records the accounts of individuals, including enslaved and African-Americans, who purchased goods from Crawford. Information found in the accounts include name of individual, date of transaction, goods purchased, service rendered, form of payment, amount owed, and amount paid. Goods sold include tobacco, corn, whiskey, coffee, meal, and bacon. Services rendered include pasturing livestock, renting out wagons, Forms of payment include cash, credit, labor, and barter of goods including chickens, iron kettles, and flour. Includes index.
  - John S. Crawford Plantation Account Book 1859-1869
- William J. Ficklin Account Book, 1902-1904, 1 volume
  Scope and Content: William J. Ficklin Account book, 1902-1904, records produce bought by various individuals.
  - William J. Ficklin Account Book 1902-1904
- C. R. Mann Book C, 1879-1880, 1 volume
  Historical Information: C. Ross Mann owned a mercantile business called C.R. Mann located in the town of Batesville in Albemarle County, Virginia. The ledger was used as an exhibit in the chancery suit Wingo, Ellett, and Crump, etc., versus Mann and Wood heard in the Albemarle County Circuit Court. The dispute centered over money owed Wingo, Ellett, and Crump by C. Ross Mann and his business partner William L. Wood. According to Mann, all the business' financial records were held by Wood which Wood denied.
  Scope and Content: C. R. Mann Book C, 1879-1880, is a ledger that records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, type of transaction, item purchased, and amount owed or paid, and form of payment. Items sold include tobacco, food (bacon, beef, eggs, sugar), tools, farm implements, nails, tools, and cloth. forms of payment include cash, credit, and barter of items such as wheat, cherries, and chickens.
  Also see: Albemarle County (Va.) Chancery Cause, Wingo, Ellett, and Crump], etc. versus Mann and Wood, 1890-022.
  - C. R. Mann Book C 1879-1880
- William T. McAllister Daybook, 1876-1877, 1 volume
  Scope and Content: William T. McAllister Daybook, 1876-1877, records accounts of individuals for purchases made within the tavern. Information includes name of account holder, quantity of purchases, and total of accounts.
  - William T. McAllister Daybook 1876-1877
- Price, Phares, and Randolph Real Estate Listings, Undated, 1 volume
  Scope and Content: Price, Phares, and Randolph real estate listings, undated, records physical descriptions of 115 properties that have been offered for sale. The properties are primarily large farms with dwelling houses. Other properties have smokehouses, icehouses, or quarters for enslaved individuals available.
  - Price, Phares, and Randolph Real Estate Listings Undated
- John B. Spiece Plantation Ledger, 1831-1890 (bulk 1857-1890), 1 volume
  Historical Information::John B. Spiece was a lawyer and an enslaver in Albemarle County.
  Scope and Content: John B. Spiece Plantation Ledger, 1831-1890 (bulk 1857-1890), records debits and credits incurred in the administration of his plantation. Accounts include wages for laborers employed in picking fruit, milling, and planting; board for laborers; and supplies such as clothing bought for his enslaved individuals or tools and farm implements. Page 477 records the names of ten enslaved individuals owned by Spiece and their date of death.
  - John B. Spiece Plantation Ledger 1831-1890 (bulk 1857-1890)
- Unidentified Newspaper Account Book, 1831-1836, 1 volume
  Scope and Content: Unidentified Newspaper Account Book, 1831-1836, records individual accounts of customers. Information found in accounts accounts include name of customer, date of transaction, service rendered, amount owed and paid, and form of payment. Services rendered primarily relate to publishing advertisements for customers such as property sales including enslaved individuals. The account book also includes a list of names of subscribers who lived locally, in-state, and out-of-state. Includes index.
  - Unidentified Newspaper Account Book 1831-1836
- Woods and Company Records, 1897-1898, 2 volumes
  Scope and Content: Woods and Company Account Book, 1897-1898, contains accounts of goods bought and sold. Items include produce, eggs, flour, sugar, and coffee.
  Woods and Company Order Book No. 4, 1897-1898, records name of customer, date of purchase, grocery items (such as coffee, butter, tobacco, and bacon) purchased, and price of purchase.
  - Woods and Company Account Book 1897-1898
  - Woods and Company Order Book No. 4 1897-1898